But for the moment, since we have found no evidence for new phenomena, let us suppose that the particles that we know today, including the Higgs boson, are the only elementary particles in nature, even at energies much larger than what we have explored so far. Let's see where this hypothesis is going to lead us. We will find a surprising and intriguing result about our universe, and to explain my point, let me first tell you what the Higgs is about, and to do so, we have to go back to one tenth of a billionth of a second after the Big Bang. And according to the Higgs theory, at that instant, a dramatic event took place in the universe. Space-time underwent a phase transition. It was something very similar to the phase transition that occurs when water turns into ice below zero degrees. But in our case, the phase transition is not a change in the way the molecules are arranged inside the material,
Pero por el momento, ya que no se ha encontrado evidencia de nuevos fenómenos, esto nos deja suponer que las partículas que conocemos hoy en día, incluyendo el bosón de Higgs, son las únicas partículas elementales en la naturaleza, incluso a energías mucho mayores que las que hemos explorado hasta ahora. Vamos a ver a donde nos llevará esta hipótesis. Nos encontraremos con un resultado sorprendente y fascinante acerca de nuestro universo; y para explicar mi punto, primero les explicaré qué es el Higgs, y para hacerlo, tenemos que retroceder a un diezmilmillonésimo de segundo después del Big Bang. Y según la teoría de Higgs, en ese instante, se produjo un acontecimiento dramático en el universo. El espacio-tiempo experimentó una transición de fase. Fue algo muy similar a la transición de fase que ocurre cuando el agua se convierte en hielo por debajo de los cero grados. Pero en nuestro caso, la transición de fase no es un cambio en la forma como las moléculas se organizan dentro de la materia,
but is about a change of the very fabric of space-time. During this phase transition, empty space became filled with a substance that we now call Higgs field. And this substance may seem invisible to us, but it has a physical reality. It surrounds us all the time, just like the air we breathe in this room. And some elementary particles interact with this substance, gaining energy in the process. And this intrinsic energy is what we call the mass of a particle, and by discovering the Higgs boson, the LHC has conclusively proved that this substance is real, because it is the stuff the Higgs bosons are made of. And this, in a nutshell, is the essence of the Higgs story. But this story is far more interesting than that. By studying the Higgs theory, theoretical physicists discovered, not through an experiment but with the power of mathematics, that the Higgs field does not necessarily exist only in the form that we observe today. Just like matter can exist as liquid or solid,
sino que se trata de un cambio de la estructura del espacio-tiempo. Durante esta transición de fase, el espacio vacío se llenó de una sustancia que ahora llamamos campo de Higgs. Y esta sustancia puede parecer invisible para nosotros, pero tiene una realidad física. Nos rodea todo el tiempo, al igual que el aire que respiramos en esta habitación. Y algunas partículas elementales interactúan con esta sustancia, obteniendo energía en el proceso. Y esta energía intrínseca es lo que llamamos la masa de una partícula, y al descubrir el bosón de Higgs, el GCH ha demostrado concluyentemente que esta sustancia es real, porque las cosas están constituidas por los bosones de Higgs. Y esto, en pocas palabras, es la esencia de la historia de Higgs. Pero esta historia es mucho más interesante. Mediante el estudio de la teoría de Higgs, físicos teóricos descubrieron, no a través de un experimento sino mediante el poder de las matemáticas, que el campo de Higgs no existe necesariamente solamente en la forma que observamos hoy. Al igual que la materia puede existir como líquido o sólido,
so the Higgs field, the substance that fills all space-time, could exist in two states. Besides the known Higgs state, there could be a second state in which the Higgs field is billions and billions times denser than what we observe today, and the mere existence of another state of the Higgs field poses a potential problem. This is because, according to the laws of quantum mechanics, it is possible to have transitions between two states, even in the presence of an energy barrier separating the two states, and the phenomenon is called, quite appropriately, quantum tunneling. Because of quantum tunneling, I could disappear from this room and reappear in the next room, practically penetrating the wall. But don't expect me to actually perform the trick in front of your eyes, because the probability for me to penetrate the wall is ridiculously small. You would have to wait a really long time before it happens, but believe me, quantum tunneling is a real phenomenon, and it has been observed in many systems. For instance, the tunnel diode, a component used in electronics, works thanks to the wonders of quantum tunneling. But let's go back to the Higgs field. If the ultra-dense Higgs state existed, then, because of quantum tunneling, a bubble of this state could suddenly appear in a certain place of the universe at a certain time, and it is analogous to what happens when you boil water. Bubbles of vapor form inside the water, then they expand, turning liquid into gas. In the same way, a bubble of the ultra-dense Higgs state could come into existence because of quantum tunneling. The bubble would then expand at the speed of light, invading all space, and turning the Higgs field from the familiar state into a new state. Is this a problem? Yes, it's a big a problem. We may not realize it in ordinary life, but the intensity of the Higgs field is critical for the structure of matter. If the Higgs field were only a few times more intense, we would see atoms shrinking, neutrons decaying inside atomic nuclei, nuclei disintegrating, and hydrogen would be the only possible chemical element in the universe. And the Higgs field, in the ultra-dense Higgs state, is not just a few times more intense than today, but billions of times, and if space-time were filled by this Higgs state, all atomic matter would collapse. No molecular structures would be possible, no life. So, I wonder, is it possible that in the future, the Higgs field will undergo a phase transition and, through quantum tunneling, will be transformed into this nasty, ultra-dense state? In other words, I ask myself, what is the fate of the Higgs field in our universe? And the crucial ingredient necessary to answer this question is the Higgs boson mass. And experiments at the LHC found that the mass of the Higgs boson is about 126 GeV. This is tiny when expressed in familiar units, because it's equal to something like 10 to the minus 22 grams, but it is large in particle physics units, because it is equal to the weight of an entire molecule of a DNA constituent. So armed with this information from the LHC, together with some colleagues here at CERN, we computed the probability that our universe could quantum tunnel into the ultra-dense Higgs state, and we found a very intriguing result. Our calculations showed that the measured value of the Higgs boson mass is very special. It has just the right value to keep the universe hanging in an unstable situation. The Higgs field is in a wobbly configuration that has lasted so far but that will eventually collapse. So according to these calculations, we are like campers who accidentally set their tent at the edge of a cliff. And eventually, the Higgs field will undergo a phase transition and matter will collapse into itself. So is this how humanity is going to disappear? I don't think so. Our calculation shows that quantum tunneling of the Higgs field is not likely to occur in the next 10 to the 100 years, and this is a very long time. It's even longer than the time it takes for Italy to form a stable government. (Laughter) Even so, we will be long gone by then. In about five billion years, our sun will become a red giant, as large as the Earth's orbit, and our Earth will be kaput, and in a thousand billion years, if dark energy keeps on fueling space expansion at the present rate, you will not even be able to see as far as your toes, because everything around you expands at a rate faster than the speed of light. So it is really unlikely that we will be around to see the Higgs field collapse. But the reason why I am interested in the transition of the Higgs field is because I want to address the question, why is the Higgs boson mass so special? Why is it just right to keep the universe at the edge of a phase transition? Theoretical physicists always ask "why" questions. More than how a phenomenon works, theoretical physicists are always interested in why a phenomenon works in the way it works. We think that this these "why" questions can give us clues about the fundamental principles of nature. And indeed, a possible answer to my question opens up new universes, literally. It has been speculated that our universe is only a bubble in a soapy multiverse made out of a multitude of bubbles, and each bubble is a different universe with different fundamental constants and different physical laws. And in this context, you can only talk about the probability of finding a certain value of the Higgs mass. Then the key to the mystery could lie in the statistical properties of the multiverse. It would be something like what happens with sand dunes on a beach. In principle, you could imagine to find sand dunes of any slope angle in a beach, and yet, the slope angles of sand dunes are typically around 30, 35 degrees. And the reason is simple: because wind builds up the sand, gravity makes it fall. As a result, the vast majority of sand dunes have slope angles around the critical value, near to collapse. And something similar could happen for the Higgs boson mass in the multiverse. In the majority of bubble universes, the Higgs mass could be around the critical value, near to a cosmic collapse of the Higgs field, because of two competing effects, just as in the case of sand. My story does not have an end, because we still don't know the end of the story. This is science in progress, and to solve the mystery, we need more data, and hopefully, the LHC will soon add new clues to this story. Just one number, the Higgs boson mass, and yet, out of this number we learn so much. I started from a hypothesis, that the known particles are all there is in the universe, even beyond the domain explored so far. From this, we discovered that the Higgs field that permeates space-time may be standing on a knife edge, ready for cosmic collapse, and we discovered that this may be a hint that our universe is only a grain of sand in a giant beach, the multiverse. But I don't know if my hypothesis is right. That's how physics works: A single measurement can put us on the road to a new understanding of the universe or it can send us down a blind alley. But whichever it turns out to be, there is one thing I'm sure of: The journey will be full of surprises. Thank you. (Applause)
el campo de Higgs, la sustancia que llena todo el espacio-tiempo, podría existir en dos estados. Además el estado de Higgs conocido, podría haber adoptado un segundo estado donde el campo de Higgs es miles de millones de veces más denso que lo que observamos hoy en día, y la mera existencia de otro estado del campo de Higgs plantea un problema potencial. Esto es porque, de acuerdo a las leyes de la mecánica cuántica, es posible tener transiciones entre dos estados, incluso en presencia de una barrera de energía que separe los dos estados, un fenómeno llamado, muy apropiadamente, efecto túnel cuántico. Debido al efecto túnel cuántico yo podría desaparecer de esta habitación y aparecer en la habitación de al lado, prácticamente penetrando la pared. Pero no esperen que realice el truco ante sus ojos, porque la probabilidad para mí de atravesar la pared es ridículamente pequeña. Tendrán que esperar mucho tiempo antes de que suceda, pero créanme, el efecto túnel cuántico es un fenómeno real, y se ha observado en muchos sistemas. Por ejemplo, el diodo túnel, un componente usado en electrónica, funciona gracias a las maravillas del efecto túnel cuántico. Pero volvamos al campo de Higgs. Si existiera el estado Higgs ultra denso, entonces, debido al efecto túnel cuántico, una burbuja de este estado podría aparecer de repente en algún lugar del universo en un momento determinado, lo que es análogo a lo que sucede cuando el agua hierve. Las burbujas de vapor se forman dentro del agua, luego se expanden, convirtiendo líquido en gas. De la misma manera, una burbuja del estado Higgs ultra denso podría venir a la existencia por el efecto túnel cuántico. Luego se expandiría la burbuja a la velocidad de la luz, invadiendo todo el espacio y convirtiendo el campo de Higgs del estado familiar al nuevo estado. ¿Esto es un problema? Sí, es un gran problema. No puede ocurrirnos en la vida cotidiana, pero la intensidad del campo de Higgs es crítica para la estructura de la materia. Si el campo de Higgs fuera un poco más intenso, veríamos átomos encogiéndose, neutrones decayendo dentro de los núcleos atómicos, los núcleos desintegrándose, y el hidrógeno sería el único elemento químico posible en el universo. El campo de Higgs, en su estado de Higgs ultra denso, no solo es un par de veces más intenso que en la actualidad, sino miles de millones de veces, y si el espacio-tiempo se llenara con ese estado de Higgs, toda la materia atómica colapsaría. No existirían estructuras moleculares, ni vida. Entonces, me pregunto, ¿es posible que en el futuro, el campo de Higgs sufra una transición de fase y, a través del efecto túnel cuántico, se transforme en este estado desagradable, ultra denso? En otras palabras, me pregunto, ¿cuál es el destino del campo de Higgs en nuestro universo? Y el ingrediente crucial necesario para responder a esta pregunta es la masa del bosón de Higgs. Y experimentos en el GCH encontraron que la masa del bosón de Higgs es aproximadamente 126 GeV. Esto es pequeño cuando se expresa en unidades familiares, porque es igual a 10 a la menos 22 gramos. Pero es grande en las unidades de la física de partículas, porque es igual al peso de una molécula entera de un constituyente del ADN. Armados con esta información del GCH, junto con algunos colegas aquí en el CERN, calculamos la probabilidad de que nuestro universo pudiera atravesar el túnel cuántico al estado de Higgs ultra denso, y hemos encontrado un resultado muy interesante. Nuestros cálculos han demostrado que el valor medido de la masa de bosón de Higgs es muy especial. Tiene justo el valor correcto para mantener suspendido al universo en una situación inestable. El campo de Higgs está en una configuración inestable que se ha mantenido hasta ahora pero que finalmente se derrumbará. Así que según estos cálculos, somos como los campistas que accidentalmente ponen su tienda en el borde de un precipicio. Y finalmente, el campo de Higgs experimentará una transición de fase y la materia se derrumbará en sí misma. ¿Así es cómo la humanidad va a desaparecer? No lo creo. Nuestro cálculo muestra que ese efecto túnel cuántico del campo de Higgs no es probable que se produzca en los próximos 10 a la 100 años y eso es mucho tiempo. Es incluso más que el tiempo que tarda Italia en formar un gobierno estable. (Risas) Aún así, para entonces ya nos habremos ido hace tiempo. En unos 5 mil millones de años, nuestro Sol se convertirá en una gigante roja, tan grande como la órbita de la Tierra, y nuestra Tierra será "kaput", y en un billón de años, si la energía oscura sigue impulsando la expansión del espacio al ritmo actual, ni siquiera podrán ver más allá de sus pies, porque todo a su alrededor se expandirá a un ritmo más rápido que la velocidad de la luz. Así que es muy poco probable que estemos por allí para ver el colapso del campo de Higgs. Pero la razón para interesarme en la transición del campo de Higgs es porque quiero abordar la cuestión, ¿por qué es la masa del bosón de Higgs tan especial? ¿Por qué es justo la correcta para mantener el universo en el borde de una transición de fase? Los físicos teóricos siempre preguntan "por qué". Mucho más que "cómo" funciona un fenómeno, los físicos teóricos siempre están interesados en "por qué" un fenómeno funciona de la manera que funciona. Creemos que estas preguntas de "por qué" nos pueden dar pistas acerca de los principios fundamentales de la naturaleza. Y en efecto, una posible respuesta a mi pregunta abre nuevos universos, literalmente. Se ha especulado que nuestro universo es solo una burbuja en un multiverso jabonoso hecho de una multitud de burbujas, y cada burbuja es un universo diferente con diferentes constantes fundamentales y diferentes leyes físicas. Y en este contexto, solo se puede hablar de la probabilidad de encontrar un determinado valor de la masa de Higgs. Entonces la clave del misterio podría residir en las propiedades estadísticas del multiverso. Sería algo parecido a lo que sucede con las dunas de arena en una playa. En principio, uno podría imaginar encontrar dunas de arena con cualquier ángulo de pendiente en una playa, y sin embargo, los ángulos de inclinación de las dunas de arena típicamente miden alrededor de 30, 35 grados. Y la razón es simple: el viento acumula la arena y la gravedad la hace caer. Como resultado, la mayoría de las dunas de arena tienen ángulos de inclinación alrededor del valor crítico, cerca del colapso. Y algo similar podría suceder para la masa del bosón de Higgs en el multiverso. En la mayoría de los universos burbuja, la masa de Higgs podría estar alrededor del valor crítico, cerca de un colapso cósmico del campo de Higgs, debido a dos efectos en competencia, igual que en el caso de la arena. Mi historia no tiene un fin, porque aún no sabemos el final de la historia. Esto es ciencia en progreso, y para resolver el misterio, necesitamos más datos, y espero que el GCH pronto añada nuevas pistas a esta historia. Solo un número, la masa del bosón de Higgs, y sin embargo, de este número aprendemos mucho. Yo empecé desde una hipótesis, que las partículas conocidas son todo lo que hay en el universo, incluso más allá del dominio explorado hasta ahora. De esto, descubrimos que el campo de Higgs que impregna el espacio-tiempo puede estar permanentemente al filo de la navaja, listo para el colapso cósmico, y descubrimos que esta puede ser una pista de que nuestro universo es solo un grano de arena en una playa gigante, el multiverso. Pero no sé si mi hipótesis es correcta. Así es como funciona la física: una sola medición puede ponernos en el camino a una nueva comprensión del universo o nos puede enviar a un callejón sin salida. Pero en cualquier caso de una cosa estoy seguro: El viaje estará lleno de sorpresas. Gracias. (Aplausos)